[music]
All right. So, welcome to Robocoders
judgment day. Specdriven AI coding tools
face off. Um, good news, no face off.
Um, generally this talk is 3 hours long.
Uh, we're going to do it in 25 minutes.
So, it's going to look a little bit
different. We really tried to fit it
into 25 minutes. the shorter we got was
an hour. So that's kind of a very far
away from what we need to do.
>> The good thing is that the video that
Bar is talking about 3 hours video is
actually available somewhere on the
internet.
>> Yeah. [clears throat] Yeah. We will show
you where where it is. We will show you
where it is. All right. So uh we're
going to talk about two tools today
because we don't have a lot of time.
Both of them are very spec driven
centric. Um the one is uh GitHub spec
kit that was avail that is available for
a couple of months by now. um making
very interesting progress in um the
domain of specdriven development and the
other which makes all the news yesterday
and today is
Amazon Ko
>> don't despair if you are not seeing your
favorite tool right now like I said look
up this video that we were doing and you
might find your tool today we're going
to focus on these things because Kira
has opinionated way to handle u
>> spec driven development
>> and spec kit is something also
opinionated But seems to be kind of
available across the ids. You don't have
to.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So yeah. So basically if you
want to use kira spec driven development
you use ko. If you want to use specit
driven development you can use it in
almost any ID or tool but we'll talk
about it. Yeah. Okay. Who you are? Uh my
name is Barak. I'm a head of developer
relations at taxare. Um we do awesome
t-shirts. By the way it's Wednesday my
dudes if you didn't notice. Uh literally
it's Wednesday. Um, and if you want to
get awesome t-shirts, uh, we have them
to share the love around for good
questions, comments, naming potatoes
three times and a bunch of other fun
activities. AJ Bar on the internet. Um,
this is my dear friend and partner in
shenanigans shenanigans, Victor Gamov,
principal developer advocate of Fluent.
If you ever heard about Kafka, you've
probably heard it from Victor. If you
didn't hear about Kafka from Victor, you
should.
>> Yes. Yes,
>> wrote the book about Kafka, but not
going to talk about Kafka today.
>> Not Kafka today. Edgamusa all over the
internet. Hit him up. He's awesome. Um,
Java in AI space. Interesting choice.
Um, one of the reasons why we're are
going to say some of the nasty things
about the state of AI that we're going
to say is because our Java background.
Um basically we think that state of AI
now is a a pile of um
smoking
>> markdown files. Yes.
>> Pile of smoking markdown files.
>> Yes. Exactly. Which is terrible.
Shouldn't be that way because we are
Java developers and Okay. Um yeah. Uh
you go to show.taxer.com.
Uh in couple of hours you will see there
a page dedicated for this talk. Yeah. uh
that uh it's going to have uh also a
system engineering.com. It will have the
slides. It will have the video that we
are recording right now. It will have
all the links um to everything that
we're going to talk about and it will
have a raffle uh to say thank you for
for for being here. Um there is a QR
code. This QR code actually takes you to
a previous version of this talk which is
like 3 hours. Um and expect a new
version of this talk in this the same
space uh later today. Um all right so uh
as you know specd driven development is
all the rage everybody are speaking
about it only today in this conference
there are at least three talks about
cure for example and this is one of them
and there is there was a workshop
yesterday and um there is tons of
content about it and this is very
>> premium agreement about this so that you
know we're going to take this tool or
they will going to take this tool and
talk about it's just awesome that's why
you know the the good people to get up
it and start using it.
>> What what is specd driven development?
>> What is specd driven development?
>> Yes,
>> it's a process where you have a few
steps. One step is that you need to
define requirements. So your application
you becoming more as as a product
manager. So and as requirements needs to
be good. If you have a bad requirements,
we have a slide for that about bad
requirements. After we define
requirements, we need to go to define a
plan. how we're going to be solving
those requirements and usually it
involves some of the you know design
decisions how the components would work.
>> For example, if you make a beef stew,
one of the steps will be boil your
potatoes.
>> Boil your potatoes.
>> That would be one of the steps.
>> Um second and the third thing is that uh
we can break down this into particular
tasks that will be used as a
implementation. So a little bit of
waterfall kind of like a style of doing
>> and the tasks opposite two steps will be
with the potatoes will be wash the
potatoes and then put them in water and
Yeah. Exactly. Yep. Yep. Uh and then
after we did the the the tasks
>> we have a autonomous ability to
implement those tasks.
>> Uh the next step will be let the AI
implement those tasks. Right? So that's
that's in a nutshell what those tools
do. um Kira and Specky do it a little
bit differently. You will see the
difference soon. Uh but that's kind of
the the big um the big thing, right? So
um what do we have in store? Um
basically this process formalized to um
different degree in in both of those
tools. Um
>> how we going to validate that what we're
getting right things kind of like one of
the things would be you know the code
reviews right. So we have our
requirements described. We have uh the
tasks specified the task linked to our
requirements. So so good right so we can
take the code.
>> So this is a very good question right in
the end of the day we did all this
process and we ended up with code that
does something. How do we know that this
code actually does what we want it to
do? I mean last we we looked we looked
at the steps
>> and the steps looks great. Mhm.
>> Next thing we know, we have code
running. How do we know?
>> What? What do you do?
>> What would you do?
>> What do you do? It's it's not a rhetoric
question. How do you know?
>> Review the code.
>> Review the code. Thank you very much.
Now, there is one thing that developers
hate and that's reading someone else's
code.
>> Yes.
>> And that includes And that excludes you,
your code from six months ago.
>> So, what about So, we're doing this like
AI thingy. What about if the AI will
validate our code?
>> Wait a second. I have more jokes about
reading your own code. Okay, more jokes,
>> right? So, um why do we actually but but
right so we said like we hate reading
other people's code but code reviews
actually exist and and and work right to
some extent. Now why why are they work?
Because mostly professional courtesy.
You have a colleague that wrote some
code like Victor wrote some code. He
made a pull request. I don't have time
for that. I'm in a completely different
context. I secretly hate this guy for
doing that, but I'm going to review the
pull request because he's my colleague.
I need to eat lunch with him tomorrow
and I better do it. Uh, you know what my
code review will be?
>> Looks good to me.
>> Yeah, ship it. LJTM
>> ship it.
>> Right. Right now, so generally quer
views are not good. Now remove the human
that you respect from the loop. What are
the chances that someone is going to do
a proper review of the code that AI
wrote? Not much. But Victor had an idea.
>> Yes. So we're doing AI. It's like smart
enough.
>> Yes. So what
>> how about we going to ask AI to validate
it?
>> Oh, there was something like there was
some some some way to validate that code
does what we want. Anyone has any ideas?
Something starts with T.
tests. Maybe
>> that's the test
>> test. That's a great idea.
>> It's a t-shirt.
>> It's a t-shirt. Definitely. Whoever came
up
>> for for this card after this,
>> whoever came up with this test thing
deserve a t-shirt. This is great.
>> Absolutely.
>> Now, [snorts]
what is the pro? Who's going to write
the test?
>> AI.
>> AI is going to write a test.
>> We
>> right now. So, basically, we have AI
writing tests for the code that AI
wrote.
What can possibly go wrong?
>> AI rates itself. It's saying it's
incredible. It's
>> it's it's perfect.
>> That's absolutely right.
>> Right. So, I mean,
>> how is that different than
>> humans will write tests based on
specification and won't adjust them to
the bugs in code? You AI is definitely
going to do that.
Circular verification is terrible. And
if you ask AI to write tests for their
code, they're going to play with both of
them until it's all passes. Even if it
doesn't make any sense, don't do what
you need, not related to the specs that
you asked. And very very far away from
everything that it you wanted to do. And
and that's because not because AI is
evil, although there are some research
that it is. It's because AI is just a
bunch of stupid monkeys.
Um you know the saying if you take
infinite amount of monkeys
>> give them infinite amount of typewriters
>> and give them infinite amount of time in
the end of the day they will write
Shakespeare. Now our AI models is
exactly the same. It's a bunch of
monkeys with GPUs instead of typewriters
and they are skewed towards presenting
the right answer a little bit better
than randomness. But in the end of the
day, the scholastic nature of the AI
systems and the non-deterministic
nature of AI systems guarantees that the
results will be a little bit different
every time. Something will be
Shakespeare, something will be
Shakespeareish,
something will be very far removed from
Shakespeare. So what we definitely don't
want to do definitely don't want to do
is trust the monkeys
>> in anything remotely related to our
production systems.
>> Yeah.
>> So saying that AI can actually verify
our AI is a very bad idea.
>> Yeah.
>> What do we do instead?
>> So we need to come up with a formal ways
of verification. enters out, you know,
we we might have to step in at some
point and interfere.
>> And we present you the
>> And we present you intent integrity
chain. That's kind of like a step up
with the on top of the specdriven
development that will include certain
interesting steps.
>> Now, it's not very different. We start
with the same idea. We need to formalize
the requirements. Then we review the
requirements with humans, human eyes
because requirements are text. and agree
that everything is good. Next step, we
let the machine create specs. Again,
very similar to what the spec driven
development does today. And we review
the specs because the specs are human
readable.
>> So every every step
>> important important stuff. Important
stuff. Wait a second. Wait. Yeah.
Ready?
>> It's video or audio?
>> It's both.
>> Both.
>> Okay. Now it's video. The previous one
was stills.
All right.
>> It's gonna explode my Instagram network
after that. Yeah. So each every step
will require human interaction. So this
step
>> needs to be validated by humans saying
that yes is is all good. It's all right.
>> So let's go.
>> And here is where interesting stuff
happens. Spec as you will hear uh from
our colleagues about about Kira has a
very particular type of text. They are
not only human readable, they're also
machine parsible.
And the fact that they are machine
parsible, the given when then structure
allows tests to be automatically,
deterministically,
algorithmically three amazing words in
one sentence.
>> Yes, it's like a three potatoes that
you're supposed to be saying.
>> I already did the potato. You already
covered. Okay, I covered the potato plus
one like extra potato.
automatically deterministically and
algorithmically generated from the
specs. No monkey is involved.
>> Yeah. Isn't it amazing?
>> It's amazing. And in this case, um it is
something that we can trust. And again,
we can if we don't like those, we can
throw it away. It's tests.
>> After the tests are generated, we know
for sure that tests match the spec,
right? We know for sure that spec match
the the requirements. And call me call
my if you don't agree with me
that we know it for sure. And once we
have the tests nailed down, we can ask
the monkeys to write code until our
tests are passing.
Yes.
>> Are you referring to only technical
specs or also functional nonunctional?
>> It's a very good question. The area of
how do we write the specs? So they will
cover functional, non-functional and any
other
types of requirements in the same format
of given when then it's an open
question. You probably can cover more
than 90%. even um uh load requirements
even security requirements all can be
formulated in in given when then
structure there are probably some
requirements that couldn't and can we
come with a better way of specking
probably at the moment this is what we
have all right so this looks good let's
repeat it now with colored arrows
because this is what we do okay so
software definition documents are prompt
llm create the specs
Everybody read the specs and approve and
agree that the specs represent the uh
the requirements. Algorithm generate the
tests. No monkeys involved. Monkeys
implement the read only test until they
pass. Beautiful. Beautiful.
>> Yeah,
>> there is another problem.
>> Here's another problem. Like we do have
a tools that designed around certain
ideas. So we talk about like uh
specdriven development and stuff, right?
So the
we need to bridge this gap because this
they those fols don't know this.
>> I have like wait a second I have
>> better segway.
>> Yes I have better segway. Exactly. Uh
what
>> who knows what is that?
>> What's that?
>> Any back to future fans?
>> Um if you're old enough to remember Back
to the Future movies. This is Mr.
Fusion. Mr. Fusion is an amazing uh
engine.
>> Yes.
>> That converts what?
>> Garbage.
>> Garbage into
>> energy.
>> Energy. What we have with AI and that's
my best joke of the of the day I promise
you is inverse Mr. fusion. We put in a
lot of energy and get
>> garbage.
>> Garbage.
>> Huh?
>> Yeah.
>> Exactly.
>> Right.
>> Yeah. Landed. Land it perfectly.
>> Uh now, uh I I bet you all can relate,
right? Uh for sure. One of the reason is
where our LLMs get the knowledge.
>> How many of you know what's the uh P
stands in GPT?
>> No one.
>> Pre-train.
>> Pre-trained. What does it mean?
>> Means that
>> you don't have to train for each
individual.
>> It means that the training is over.
>> Training already happened the moment you
already started. It's pre-trained.
>> And the problem with that this usually
signifies certain like cut off date. So
the certain date date in in our reality
that corresponds to all the events that
happened like before this date. meaning
that it doesn't know about Java 25 maybe
because the model was trained before
release of Java 25 or new version of
spring boot or put your own framework in
it
>> closed source that AI never heard about
>> especially enterprise repositories
that'll have your corporate code that
would be you know you know
>> we need to speed up okay right so
pre-trained model knowledge is nice but
not enough one of the reasons of
environmental fusion general web search
our modern tools can search the web and
give you results. It's nice, but
probably not good enough because there's
tons of garbage out there, incorrect
information, answers on Stack Overflow,
and other improper sources to look at.
What about we teach our AI to read the
manual?
Make AI read the manual.
How about this?
>> Yeah.
>> How do we How do we do it? There are a
couple of ways. First is uh Victor
>> first we think that you know we're using
the the uh how it's called the server
that already precached or index some of
documentation around the world. So
context 7 is a great service that
exposes some of the uh information to
LLM through MCP server. It's the topic
for another talk but essentially think
about this uh LLM will be able to speak
and find any information about any
library in internet. super useful tool
uh incredibly simple and just
>> two downsides of uh context 7 first only
public knowledge only public APIs only
public libraries there you won't put
your closed source libraries to context
7 to like serve the entire internet and
the second is only latest version
>> y
>> if now you are stuck on older version of
software um that maybe not supported
anymore or end of life first of all you
need to tax your services. So talk to me
and second you won't find the
documentation in context 7. What you can
do then is Tessle. Thank you Tessel for
hosting us in this conference. So Tessle
think about it as your both external
public source of knowledge for AI but
also cached private in-house source of
knowledge for AI. You can put there your
clos libraries. You can put there not
the latest version. You can use spring
boot 2. You can use for spring framework
4. You can use Java 8 documentation for
there. And then your AI will know all
that and will know it perfectly. All
right. So you ready to fix um specdriven
development?
>> Yes. So let's let's six minutes. It's a
probably perfect time to fix specific
development. First of all, we have a
Kira here. Um what I personally like
about this it has a very nicely
integrated UI components that will um
since we're working on this particular
feature is application that needs to
communicate through rest interface with
the bulb and light the bulb with the
color light that uh this application
will read from webcam. Don't don't think
about this right now. Find the video
internet. It's actually pretty fun. We
hanging around. The reason why we bring
this bulb because it's some sort of like
obscure library that LLM probably don't
know how to use. However, we can uh you
know use all the tools that we
described. So first thing is that uh the
Kro has support for context 7 uh we need
to explicitly tell it how to do this and
the one of the ways how you can do this
in JK ids is using things called
steering or guide rails. Different ids
call it differently. For example, this
steering which says there's a critical
rule before writing any code you must
always consult MCP context 7 MCP for
library specific APIs patterns and best
practices. So every time when it will
try to code it needs to follow this rule
you see because it's all capital all
caps meaning that it's important thing
that the the model needs to take
seriously
>> very important.
>> So we have uh now we have a the
specdriven development here. So we have
requirements, we have design that was
generated. See even like some uh some
ASKI art for uh for you know generating
>> solid design
>> solid solid you know but broken but
anyway so there specification has like
different methods what to invoke. So
basically we have it and most
importantly we have a task list. What we
don't have
>> uh we don't have tests.
>> Yeah we don't have this generated test
thingy. Terrible terrible
>> for that matter. uh we do have the
concept of the agent hooks where uh
where we can put this uh some some
generic prompts and in this particular
case prompt will say something like this
uh let's go hooks put it here and
essentially what it says create uh read
requirements read design and now create
test files following TDD principles that
should be blah blah blah executable
covered all the stories in requirements
a proper testing framework work based on
technical stack. So it will we we can
say specific framework but in this
particular case we're saying like choose
whatever want to do JUnit go for it. If
you want to do testing G it's up to you.
So um
>> and what is the hook for this?
>> Oh the most importantly that every time
when we will be updating tasks uh this
is like uh the task file that will
include our tasks we will run this hook.
So I will go and uh create this hook and
show you how this would work um in in in
this integrated UI. So I'm going into
say like my task list. We'll take give
it a moment because the um the
conference Wi-Fi and we're in the
basement. So hopefully it will okay hook
was created and it will automatically
trigger whenever we should say not
created by saved. That's one of the
things that uh so if I will run this
task in this particular case set up the
project structure. So I expecting this
will go and generate some test for me.
So task in progress. So it will go ahead
create the maven dependencies spring
boot blah blah blah and we automatically
see in here that uh autogenerate the
tests and it would be cute meaning that
there is a task in Q that will be
executed here and after that um uh we're
going to invoke those things back too.
All right. And yep.
>> All right. uh test kit uh I have test
kit uh running with GitHub compiler in
Visual Studio Code. Uh TestKit can run
in tons of different uh models uh AI
tools uh clo code like really everything
that you can think about in any editor
cursor windsurf etc etc. And this what
you see here are the suggested actions.
>> Oh thank you. Uh where is it? Where is
it? Where is it? Uh, I need to do sorry
I need to do this and now I need to do
this this.
Come on. Where is my Okay, here we go.
Sorry about that. Uh, yeah. So, uh,
those those are those are the commands
that I can run as um
um as specit commands that will do all
the steps uh of our spec generation. And
you can see here constitution and that's
the steering whatever steering is called
in kirao that's like the golden rules
write code or like this kind of stuff
and then specify we describe what we
want to build we will it will create a
spec and then plan this is the technical
specification uh we're going to use java
25 and spring boot 4 etc etc uh tasks
will break it to the smallest tasks
possible like wash your potatoes and
then implement again. No code you there
is sorry no test there is no
no step
>> notion of
>> no step for creating test which is as we
spoke not great. So, what we're going to
do, and this is one of the things that
both fascinate and terrify me, is we're
going to add two markdown files that
will completely change how spec kit
works. It blows my mind. All our
industry now AI industry is all based on
bunch of markup files. It's terrifying.
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
>> Speaking about pile of the
smoldering smoldering markdown files. So
uh we're going to add an agent uh sorry
new file we're going to uh to add an
agent which is called testify. Testify
will be our new step and this is a
definition of a real agent in in
copilot. So what we are going to write
here is what this um uh what this agent
does and what we say here is like you
are an agent and responsible for test
construction. This agent is going to
generate the tests and then we're going
to add another file to the prompts and
this will add this new step that you um
that we spoke about. So this is sorry
that's definitely not the right name
file. Um
where is my
rename
>> F6?
>> Uh yeah probably
um where is it?
Uh
this yes and this is um this is going to
add this extra step and this is actually
also um a file which is a prompt
[snorts] right. So this is actually what
the prompt will be that will be
generated automatically for us to this
agent once I added those two files. Now
suddenly I have here
specify testify. Testify. Where is my
testify?
>> Yep. Uh, nope. That's did something
wrong. But we're out of time. So if I
added it correctly,
>> I would have here an absolutely new
prompt
that would generate the tests with the
new agent that is in charge of writing
the test correctly. And I can add as
much information to this agent as I want
of how do I think that I need to those
tests to be.
>> And then I can also add a shelf a shell
script that will run
in the beginning of the implementation
phase making those tests read only. And
if I do that, I will prevent AI from
messing with those tests, making them
the source of truth for the
implementation. One more thing that I
wanted to add and that's correct for
Kira as well is our ability to switch
models between the tasks. You probably
don't think about it. You just run it
with one model that you like. But if you
do that, you benefit from two things.
First, there are better models for
different things. Thinking about spec,
you might use a more heavily reason
skewed model, maybe chart GPT 5.1. When
you run tests and and generate
implementation, you might want a coding
model, for example, set uh 105 or GPT
codeex or um any other one. Can I uh can
I say something in defense of this like
a pile of markdown smoldering files?
>> You have minus 3 minutes.
>> Yeah. So we talk about this a lot but I
think uh it also gives us uh some
benefits like a portability uh of the
things. So we can move between uh
different ideas since we're using the
same information and it's going to be
our source of truth for doing the things
right.
>> I'm Andre Baruk. This is Gamusa. This is
AI Native Devcon. Use this hashtag when
you are raving about this amazing talk.
Um also use intent integrity chain
hashtag and show notes.care.com in a
couple of hours. AI system engineering
in a couple of hours.
>> All the videos already there like 6
hours, 3 hours video.
>> 3 hours video, an hour video, whatever
you like. Now it will also be 25
minutes. Um thank you very much. We're
out of you.
>> Yep. Thank you. And uh
>> [music]